BETH: For most people, going to the doctor
or dentist is a routine experience, but
for individuals with autism, accessing
health and care support can be a
difficult and stressful experience.
JOE: New environments and sensory changes
can be challenging and cause anxiety.
It’s important that healthcare
professionals, are aware of the needs
for those with autism, and are able to
make the experience easier to handle.
Health and care settings should also
provide more flexibility, to adapt
to the needs of people with autism.
BETH: GPs should have a good
understanding and knowledge
about autism, and the appropriate
services to refer individuals to.
Appointments should also be long
enough to meet the communication
needs of an individual with autism.
JOE: Long waiting times for diagnosis
can put extra pressure on parents and
carers unnecessary stress to people
with autism, as this may mean longer
waits for treatment and support.
In some areas, there may be a lack
of support services for people living
with autism, including getting an
education, health and care plan ‘EHC’,
or a lack of information available
to accessing the support they need.
BETH: A high proportion of children with
autism attend mainstream schools, which
should all endeavour to do their utmost
in providing the necessary support for any
student who has special educational needs.
However, the needs of individuals
with autism as we have discussed
in other units often go further
than extra learning support.
There are specialist schools available and
other mainstream schools are well-equipped
with facilities to accommodate students
with autism, but this is not consistent.
JOE: Autism is clearly established as
a learning difficulty requiring special
education provision, and a child with
autism may be eligible for an ‘EHC’
plan once an assessment of their needs
has been made by the local authority.
This will describe their needs and
any specialist provision to meet those
needs and can be accessible from 0-25
years as long as they are in education
or training, but not at university.
The opportunities for progression onto
further education or training will vary
depending on where an individual lives.
BETH: Every further education
college should provide their students
with special educational needs,
the extra help that they need to
support them with their studies.
This includes students
on the autistic spectrum.
The special educational needs
coordinator or SENCO will be in
charge of organising any extra
learning support or general needs.
JOE: Students with autism may be able
to access extra support at university
through the institution's own additional
needs team, or SEN support team.
This may involve having access
to a specialist service such as a
note-taker during lectures or a mentor
to provide support such as balancing
workloads and accessing social
opportunities and leisure facilities.
They may also be entitled
to extra time in exams.
BETH: Engaging in leisure activities
can lower stress levels and improve mood
which can help to increase psychological
engagement and avoid unhealthy behaviours.
Sport has so many benefits, not
only as a great way to stay fit,
it can also offer a sense of
belonging and a way to make friends.
Regularly taking part in sport can provide
routine and structure and is a good
way to release stress and frustration.
Some sports clubs cater specifically for
the needs of individuals with autism.
JOE: Visiting the theatre or the cinema
can be exciting, and a great way to
explore a passion for something, but
also very challenging for individuals
with autism as they might find it
difficult to cope with big crowds.
However, some cinemas run autism friendly
screenings, where they lower sound levels
and there is more freedom to move around.
BETH: Museums can also be a great
place for individuals with autism to
explore their special interests, and
they are a great learning resource.
Many now have interactive displays
which involve all the senses.
JOE: The most important thing about
attending a leisure facility is to
first see if they have any specific
support already available, and
informing them about the visit, may
help them to give guidance about what is
available and for them to be prepared.